Hi, I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 9 of our
10-day Lip reading Challenge,
designed to help you develop
and practice your lip reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a
profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and tricks
on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity
to relationships in all areas of your life.
We're back to three mangoes with one stone
for Day 9.
We have three sounds
in our homophone group today.
The sounds are SH, CH, and J.
These sounds look alike
on the lips.
To make these sounds,
your lips are thrust forward,
almost like a square shape.
Not only that though,
there's something happening with your tongue.
Try it.
Say the words SHOP, CHOP, and JUDGE.
You may have noticed
that the blade of your tongue,
which is just behind the tip,
is touching the roof of your mouth
when you make these sounds.
Try it again: CHOP, SHOP, JUDGE.
There's another three for one
in today's practice.
You're going to be working on substitution,
a little bit of memory work,
and lip reading skills.
I'm also going to amp up
the difficulty a little bit.
I think you're ready for it.
I'm going to start with substitution practice.
So I'll say sentences with SH, CH, or J
errors and you will have to substitute
the appropriate sound
to get the right answer.
So if it's an SH error,
then you need to substitute
a CH or a J to get the right answer.
I'm also going to put some
P, B, and M and F and V errors
in there too.
Are you ready?
As always, the answers are written below.
Number 1
You think you see the word WASH,
and they seem to be talking about
a birthday present.
What is the word?
Number 2
This one has two substitutions
that you'll need to do.
So you think you see the word PATCH,
and they seem to be talking about
how proudly he wears it.
What is the word?
For number 3,
you think you see the word MUGs,
and they seem to be talking about
the mosquito season.
What's the word?
For number 4,
You think you see
the word SERVE
and they seem to be talking about
the ocean and having a good sense of balance.
What's the word?
For number 5,
you think you see
the word JOB,
but they seem to be talking about
a recipe for vegetable soup.
So what would the word be?
You can go ahead and look at the answers
for the first five now,
because now we're going
to shift gears a little bit.
For your memory work,
you will need to remember
those five words
because I'm going to say five sentences
silently and they will have
one of those words in it.
I'm not going to say
the sentences out loud,
so you'll have to rely on your memory
and all of the practice
you put in so far.
The answers are written below
if you need them.
Are you ready?
Number 1
And here's Number 1 again:
Number 2
Here it is again:
Number 3
Number 4
Here it is again:
Number 5
And here it is again:
If you like,
you can look at the answers
for the first five sentences now.
We'll go back to the
substitution practice
for sentences 6 to 10.
So you think you see the word JEER
and they seem to be talking about
spreading it around for the holidays.
What is the word?
Number 7
You think you see the word PUMPED
and they're talking about
accidentally meeting somebody.
What would the word be?
Number 8
You think you see the word WITCH
but they're talking about a birthday cake.
What would be the word?
For number 9,
You think you see the word FINE
(Hey, that rhymes!)
and they're talking about
organic farming and orchards.
So what would the word be?
Here's the last one for your substitution practice.
So you think you see the word BEACH but they're talking about
a tree with juicy fruit on it.
What would the word be?
Go ahead and check the answers below, if you like,
for numbers 6 to 10 substitution practice.
Because now you're going to be
lip reading sentences with those words in them.
And so you'll need to do a little bit of memory work too,
to remember the words.
Are you ready?
Number 6
Here it is again:
Number 7
Number 8
Here it is again:
Number 9
Number 10:
Number 10 again:
This is a “challenging” sentence.
So that's it for today.
I hope you enjoyed it
and found it helpful.
Please like this video,
subscribe to my channel,
and share it with others!
Tomorrow is the last day
of the challenge: Day 10!
And I have a surprise for you.
Bye-bye!